<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Review>
    <LINK>THE MEDIUM</LINK>
    <Article><MainTitle>The Medium Review </MainTitle>
        <ParaTitle>Split scream</ParaTitle>
        <AuthorInfo>By Tristan Ogilvie</AuthorInfo>
        <Date>Updated: 27 Jan 2021</Date>
        <DatePosted>9:05 am Posted: 27 Jan 2021 9:00 am</DatePosted>
        <Para1>There are always two sides to every story, but rarely does the audience get to
            experience them both at the same time. Such is the novel gameplay hook central to The
            Medium, an enthralling psychological horror adventure that splits your focus between a
            gloomy real-world setting and a haunting parallel spirit world, with actions performed
            in one having a measurable impact on the other. It’s a stylish and clever technique
            that’s used to consistently engaging effect, allowing for some stimulating puzzle design
            and exhilarating moments of reality-hopping cat and mouse with a truly memorable
            monster. I quickly warmed to the self-deprecating charm of The Medium’s split-screen
            scream queen, Marianne. She’s a spirit guide who is lured to an abandoned resort in the
            Polish hinterland hoping to uncover the origin of her clairvoyant abilities, and her
            consistently wry observations – delivered by actress Kelly Burke – kept the mood from
            becoming too dire in what is an otherwise intensely disturbing detective tale.
            Determining the extent of the evil atrocities that went down within the hotel’s walls
            and identifying the perpetrators soon becomes the main focus, one that I took great
            morbid delight in as I pieced together each and every sinister scrap of evidence along
            its bloodsoaked breadcrumb trail. Much of the clue gathering is admittedly fairly
            straightforward in a mechanical sense, using Marianne’s insight ability on discarded
            objects found in the world to reveal information about the fate of their owners, for
            example, or to highlight the ghostly footsteps that point the way forward. But elsewhere
            there are some satisfyingly hands-on methods you need to employ, and I particularly
            enjoyed the simple pleasure of arranging trays of photography chemicals and dunking the
            paper in the right sequence of solutions in order to develop a photo correctly in a dark
            room. (Remember developing photos? ... No? Okay.)</Para1>
        <ParaTitle>Dual Shocks</ParaTitle>
        <Para2>Of course, almost every room in The Medium is a dark room, and they only get darker.
            At predetermined points along the main story path the screen will split to reveal the
            spirit world side by side with the material world, and you’ll suddenly be controlling
            two versions of Marianne at the same time. It’s an incredibly striking contrast; on one
            side of the screen the flesh and bone Marianne will be moving along a dimly lit hotel
            corridor, on the other, her silver-haired spiritual form will be stalking through a
            hollowed-out hallway to Hell. On both sides of the divide the environments are
            exceptionally well realised, but it’s the spirit world that is particularly eerie to
            explore, with unearthly tendrils sprouting from the floors, outstretched hands clawing
            at you like stalactites from the ceiling, and your general surroundings resembling a
            nightmarish landscape the likes of which isn’t normally seen anywhere outside of a heavy
            metal album cover. On that note, in this otherworld you frequently reveal new areas by
            slashing through sheets of human skin with a blade made of bones, which also sounds like
            the opening lyric to the most metal song ever made. You frequently reveal new areas by
            slashing through sheets of human skin with a blade made of bones. “ Displaying both
            realities at the same time isn’t just done for stylish effect; there’s a practical
            purpose, too. During these times Marianne is able to trigger an out-of-body experience,
            relinquishing control of her earthly self for a short period of time in order to send
            her spiritual form to areas otherwise unreachable within the mortal realm. In fact, the
            complimentary use of mortal and spiritual abilities is paramount to solving the bulk of
            The Medium’s puzzles which, while never stumping me enough to halt the surging story
            momentum, still required a substantial amount of lateral thought that extended to either
            side of the split. This can be as simple as sending Marianne’s spirit to deliver a blast
            of energy to power the fusebox of a broken elevator or, in a more memorable sequence
            later on, manipulating the hands of a grandfather clock in the real world to scrub
            forwards and backwards through time in the spirit realm, revealing clues to a hidden
            door from the phantom presences that appear along the timeline. <Survey><SurveyTitle>Who
                    is the scariest horror game monster of all time?</SurveyTitle>
                <TotalVotes>2,870 votes</TotalVotes> Thank you 🎉 <SurveyChoices><Character>The
                        Witch</Character>
                    <Gametitle>(Left 4 Dead) </Gametitle><Percentofvotes>6.4%</Percentofvotes>
                    <Character>The Xenomorph</Character>
                    <GameTitle>(Alien: Isolation)</GameTitle>
                    <PercentOfVote>20.7%</PercentOfVote>
                    <Character>Nemesis</Character>
                    <GameTitle>(Resident Evil series)</GameTitle>
                    <PercentOfVote>13.8%</PercentOfVote>
                    <Character>Pyramid Head</Character>
                    <GameTitle>(Silent Hill series)</GameTitle>
                    <PercentOfVote>29.4%</PercentOfVote>
                    <Character>Alma Wad</Character>e <GameTitle>(F.E.A.R.)</GameTitle>
                    <PercentOfVote>10.0%</PercentOfVote>
                    <Character>Lisa</Character>
                    <GameTitle>(P.T.)</GameTitle>
                    <PerecntOfVote>19.7%</PerecntOfVote>
                </SurveyChoices></Survey>That said, it’s not just the haunted souls of the hotel
            you’ll have to contend with, but also the ghosts of horror games past. There are plenty
            of odd-shaped keys to find, valves to turn, and broken lever handles to repair, which on
            paper may sound like dated throwbacks to the likes of Alone in the Dark. However, it’s
            the use of Marianne’s reality-phasing abilities to uncover and obtain these items that
            makes The Medium feel distinct, and that kept me engaged in clearing a path through its
            increasingly ominous obstacles</Para2>. <ParaTitle>Always Leave Them Wanting
            Maw</ParaTitle><Para3> The other force propelling me forward was The Medium’s principal
            villain, The Maw. While I certainly enjoyed the strong performances from Marianne and
            the small supporting cast (both human and spiritual) it’s Troy Baker’s uncharacteristic
            and entirely unsettling turn as The Medium’s chief antagonist that really steals the
            show. <AuthorQuote>It’s Troy Baker’s uncharacteristic and entirely unsettling turn as
                The Medium’s chief antagonist that really steals the show. “</AuthorQuote> The Maw
            is a malevolent manifestation that haunts Marianne throughout her journey, first within
            the confines of the spirit world but eventually following her back into reality. Much
            like Resident Evil 2 and 3’s monstrous pursuers, The Maw can’t be killed, only avoided,
            which keeps tension levels high as you shift back and forth between realities not
            knowing how or when he’ll appear; he might burst in as his imposing demonic form in the
            spirit world, or as a more camouflaged spectral silhouette in the real one. Baker brings
            real menace to The Maw’s crazed mutterings as he stalks you through each setting,
            oscillating between guttural growls and tormented whimpering, and it’s his lumbering
            presence combined with creepy ambient sound design and an anxiety-inducing score that
            had me forging my way towards The Medium’s gripping conclusion while forever looking
            over my shoulder. 8 IMAGES I say that metaphorically, since you can’t actually look over
            your shoulder in The Medium. Well, not on purpose at least. While each of developer
            Bloober Team’s horror games to date have been in first-person, from Layers of Fear 2 to
            Observer to Blair Witch, The Medium is a strictly third-person affair, appropriating the
            multiple fixed camera angles of the early Resident Evil and Silent Hill games that
            change up from room to room. Apparently this decision was partially born out of
            necessity, since giving free control over the camera was reportedly causing nausea
            during the dual-reality sections. Yet while the many claustrophobic close-ups and
            cinematic angles certainly contribute to an ongoing sense of trepidation, The Medium
            doesn’t have the power to manipulate or disorient you as deviously as Bloober’s previous
            first-person games. It isn’t able to unsettle you by diverting your attention one way in
            order to rearrange the environment behind you, for example. It’s a hair-raising ride
            regardless, but the most disoriented I ever felt during the eight hours it took to
            complete the story was anytime the camera suddenly switched angles and I had to
            course-correct with an awkward stutter step like someone who’d just narrowly avoided
            walking into the wrong bathroom by accident.</Para3>
        <ParaTitle>Verdict </ParaTitle><Para4>The Medium uses a unique reality-shifting ability to
            bring a new dimension to some tried-and-tested genre puzzle-solving mechanics. It
            presents an intriguing mystery to unravel and adds a tangible sense of urgency to your
            investigations by placing a truly memorable villain hot on your heels. It isn’t able to
            play with perspective as effectively as some of Bloober Team’s other work, but it’s
            brilliantly paced and palpably tense. An absorbing and nerve-racking journey from the
            shriek of its first jump scare to its very last gasp, The Medium delivers a
            psychological horror adventure that’s all thriller and no filler.</Para4></Article>
</Review>
